So we're going to start our exploration into the world of frontier models by playing with the famous
そこで､ フロンティア・モデルの世界への探検を､ おそらくほとんどの方がよくご存じであろう､
GPT from OpenAI, which most of you are probably quite familiar with.
OpenAIの有名なGPTで遊ぶことから始めようと思う｡
I have a pro license, which means I get access to all of the models, and I imagine some of you do
私はプロライセンスを持っているので､ すべてのモデルにアクセスできる｡
We'll start with a softball question, the kind of question that they're so good at answering, which
ビジネス上の問題がLLMの解決策に適しているかどうか､
is how do I decide if a business problem is suitable for an LLM solution?
どうやって判断すればいいのでしょうか？
And it's useful for us because it's the kind of question that one might ask on this course.
このコースで聞かれるような質問なので､ 私たちにとっても有益だ｡
And what we'll get back, of course, is a very carefully structured and reasoned response with an introduction,
もちろん､ 返ってくるのは､ 序論､ 要約､ 問題の本質､ スケーラビリティの必要性など､
with summaries, the nature of the problem, the scalability needs.
非常に注意深く構成され､ 理路整然とした回答だ｡
No doubt there'll be stuff in here about nuance, about unstructured data, contextual understanding,
ここには､ ニュアンス､ 非構造化データ､ 文脈理解､ コスト､ メンテナンスなど､ たくさんの素晴らしい､
cost, maintenance, lots of great, well-reasoned points with a good summary to boot.
理路整然とした指摘があり､ それをうまく要約したものがあるに違いない｡
So this is the kind of thing that it's really, really good at.
だから､ これは本当に､ 本当に得意なことなんだ｡
Now I'll ask it a question, which it usually gets right, but sometimes amazingly gets wrong.
私が質問を投げかけると､ たいていは正解するが､ ときどき驚くほど間違える｡
Let's see what happens this time.
今回はどうなるか見てみよう｡
How many times does the letter A appear in this sentence?
この文章にはAという文字が何回出てくるか？
Uh, so let's see how it does.
どうなるか見てみよう｡
Uh, it's got it wrong.
ええと､ それは間違っている｡
The letter A appears five times in your sentence.
あなたの文章にはAという文字が5回出てきます｡
Sometimes it gets this right, and sometimes it gets it wrong.
それが正しいこともあれば､ 間違っていることもある｡
It's, uh, difficult to know, but.
難しいんだけどね｡
But, uh, it might shock you that, uh, it gets that wrong.
でも､ それが間違っていることにショックを受けるかもしれない｡
It doesn't mean that we humans still have an advantage in some ways.
だからといって､ 私たち人間の方がまだ有利な面もある｡
But the truth is, it's to do with the way that this information is sent into the LM.
しかし実際は､ この情報がLMに送られる方法に関係しているのだ｡
It's to do with this, this tokenization strategy.
それは､ このトークナイゼーション戦略に関係している｡
And we'll be talking more about that later.
それについては後で詳しく話す｡
But it is interesting that it gets it wrong.
しかし､ それが間違っているのは興味深い｡
Uh, I'm going to ask it one more question, which is a tricky question.
ええと､ もう1つ聞きますが､ これは難しい質問です｡
I'm going to ask it, uh, Choose the word that best completes the analogy.
この例えに最もふさわしい言葉を選んでください｡
Feather is to bird as scale is to.
フェザーは鳥にとってのスケールである｡
And then there's a few different options there.
そして､ そこにはいくつかの異なるオプションがある｡
And the best answer is in fact, reptile fish is a bit of a trick answer because fish do have scales,
というのも､ 魚には鱗があるが､ 爬虫類の鱗ほど区別できる特徴ではないからだ｡
This question I got from a website called vellum, which is a very a company that does a lot of this
この質問は､ ヴェラムというウェブサイトから得たものだ｡ ヴェラムは､ この種の分析を多く行っている会社で､
kind of analysis that we will talk about later.
後ほど紹介する｡
All right.
分かった｡
Let's switch to a different model.
別のモデルに切り替えよう｡
Let's switch to zero one preview.
ゼロワンのプレビューに切り替えよう｡
This is the model that was originally codenamed strawberry and is the strongest of OpenAI's models,
これはもともとstrawberryというコードネームで呼ばれていたモデルで､ OpenAIの最強モデルであり､
only available to Pro subscribers, but it will ultimately be available to everyone, and it gives you
プロ契約者のみが利用できるが､ 最終的には誰でも利用できるようになり､ 今後の展開を予感させる｡
It uses a sort of chain of reasoning approach to think through questions.
一種の推理の連鎖のようなアプローチで問題を考えていく｡
Let's ask it the same question how many times does the letter A appear in this sentence.
同じ質問をしてみよう｡ この文章にAという文字は何回出てくるだろうか？
See if it can do better.
もっとうまくやれるかどうか見てみよう｡
It's thinking.
考えているんだ｡
You can see how it takes longer for sure.
確かに時間がかかるのはわかるだろう｡
Counting letter frequencies.
文字の頻度を数える｡
That sounds promising.
それは期待できそうだ｡
Taking a closer look.
よく見てみよう｡
Good to know.
知っておいて損はない｡
And it gets the right the answer.
そして､ 正しい答えを導き出す｡
Correct.
その通りだ｡
The letter A appears four times in the sentence.
文中にAという文字が4回出てくる｡
Once in many, uh, once within the quotes and twice in the word appear.
引用符の中に1回､ "appear "の中に2回｡
So it is correct.
だから正しい｡
Very good.
とても良い｡
Uh, and then let's also ask strawberry.
ええと､ それからイチゴにも聞いてみよう｡
Oh, one preview this, uh, this puzzle and let's see how it can approach this.
ああ､ このパズルをプレビューして､ このパズルにどうアプローチできるか見てみよう｡
It's considering choosing the right analogy that's also promising cultivating.
適切な例えを選択することは､ 有望な育成でもある｡
And it gives the correct answer reptile.
そして正解は爬虫類｡
So this gives you a sense of the different models, some of the different strengths between them from
これで､ GPTの4つのゼロとゼロ・ワンのプレビューから､ 異なるモデル､ 異なる強さのいくつかを感じてもらえるだろう｡